Hello everybody. Welcome to the Orthodox
Traditionalist Publications. I'll be
doing an interview here with my bishop,
Metropolitan Demetrius of the Genuine
Orthodox Church of Greece here in
America, the American Metropolis. You're
on the bless. It's good to be with you.
>> God bless you. God bless you.
>> This has been it's been a glad that
we're
>> they help us indeed. So, this has been
I've been people have been asking me for
this. It's been a long time. I know you
it's hard to get your get your time
because I've been
busy. You've been extremely busy. So,
thank you for being here with me today.
>> Is that good?
>> So, people are wondering, can you tell
us uh people are interested in the GOC
as you know there your your inbox is
getting
completely overwhelmed with inquiry and
so I'm glad I can help.
>> Phone calls too. phone phone calls,
emails, visits to the monastery. I'm
glad that that's we're growing. But so
could you tell us about your your your
history, Orthodox history with Roore and
HTM, and the GOC
and uh your
and uh your life as the first hierarch
in in in America.
>> Okay. Well,
I was brought up in the church, thank
God. My parents uh come from a village
in northern Greece
uh was a Slav speaking village and uh so
you know it was hearing the church
savonic of course was somewhat
recognizable but I I grew up mostly the
the Greek parish of St. Nario in Toronto
and uh my uh my grandmother left a very
deep influence in my life. She was uh
the one that led us all to that church
basically.
Her sister actually the the parish was
uh we had around 500 families. It's very
large parish
and um St. Tyrus himself would appear to
people and sometimes and tell them I
want you to go to my parish. And uh
my grandmother had doubts actually about
the uh old calendar because you know the
old-timers in that area were uh very
much staunch defenders of the uh
traditions of the church. And so um
uh she had a few uh major miracles which
confirmed
that uh that it's not a small issue that
the church needs to hold on to the
traditions that disunityity in the
church was uh began with the change of
the calendar and of course it to this
day um those people in those
jurisdictions patriarchets don't
celebrate together and sometimes they
celebrate two times
uh you know clergy from Greece, bishops
from Greece will go to Mount Aus and
celebrate the old calendar in the day
celebrate the new calendar
and uh she was just a very saintly
person you know she she a lot of people
could say you know my grandmother
brought me to church and all this kind
of stuff but it was it was really beyond
that it was super human it was uh was
someone who um
just loved God so much you read
sometimes in the lives of the saints
It's it you know only grace could could
u aid these people to be so cetical and
um so without any exception it was
always all day all night prayers
she just continuously making the sign on
the cross always praying and and just a
beautiful example which I cannot really
imitate quite frankly because it was
above
uh and and there were just so many signs
of real grace in this person and and the
first few years of my life we sort of
lived in
area of Toronto which is called Danforth
very close to Greek town.
So we lived very close just a couple
blocks away from my grandmother and so
as a child I would I would spend a lot
of time there at sleepover for extended
periods of time. Then we moved and then
they would spend extended periods, my
grandparents would uh spend extended
periods of time with us. And the system
that we had was that my grandfather
would stay in the um spare room and my
grandmother would stay in my room and
she she'd just be praying all night all
all night. And she just like literally
all night tears growing going through
her eyes. I remember you know waking up
with her hands up and she just streaming
tears
and uh it didn't bother me. I was
because you know from the time I was as
long as I can remember um
you know I was very much into uh I went
to church and I I I I loved going to
church and I
>> I said my my mother God bless her you
know she brought us up in the faith but
my grandmother was the one my mother was
pious my grandmother's
holy
and um
so she left an influence in the family
everybody
went to uh synctic taris. She sort of
led the way
and um
as I said it was it was really all night
long prayers and and unbelievable
fasting and uh so I I grew up hearing
things from the old country. You know
how they uh it was almost like we were
in this protected little
>> nucleus and uh she would tell me about
things back in the old country and
sometimes about specifically about the
church calendar issues and how the
faithful and how the grandmother who
lived with her
who subsequently was uh her ending was
so blessed that she told everybody okay
I'm going to be dying she
>> she yeah what happened was that her
guard heard an angel appeared to her and
told her, "I'm taking your soul."