Hello everybody. Welcome to the Orthodox
Traditionalist Publications. I'll be
doing an interview here with my bishop,
Metropolitan Demetrius of the Genuine
Orthodox Church of Greece here in
America, the American Metropolis. You're
on the bless. It's good to be with you.
>> God bless you. God bless you.
>> This has been it's been a glad that
we're
>> they help us indeed. So, this has been
I've been people have been asking me for
this. It's been a long time. I know you
it's hard to get your get your time
because I've been
busy. You've been extremely busy. So,
thank you for being here with me today.
>> Is that good?
>> So, people are wondering, can you tell
us uh people are interested in the GOC
as you know there your your inbox is
getting
completely overwhelmed with inquiry and
so I'm glad I can help.
>> Phone calls too. phone phone calls,
emails, visits to the monastery. I'm
glad that that's we're growing. But so
could you tell us about your your your
history, Orthodox history with Roore and
HTM, and the GOC
and uh your
and uh your life as the first hierarch
in in in America.
>> Okay. Well,
I was brought up in the church, thank
God. My parents uh come from a village
in northern Greece
uh was a Slav speaking village and uh so
you know it was hearing the church
savonic of course was somewhat
recognizable but I I grew up mostly the
the Greek parish of St. Nario in Toronto
and uh my uh my grandmother left a very
deep influence in my life. She was uh
the one that led us all to that church
basically.
Her sister actually the the parish was
uh we had around 500 families. It's very
large parish
and um St. Tyrus himself would appear to
people and sometimes and tell them I
want you to go to my parish. And uh
my grandmother had doubts actually about
the uh old calendar because you know the
old-timers in that area were uh very
much staunch defenders of the uh
traditions of the church. And so um
uh she had a few uh major miracles which
confirmed
that uh that it's not a small issue that
the church needs to hold on to the
traditions that disunityity in the
church was uh began with the change of
the calendar and of course it to this
day um those people in those
jurisdictions patriarchets don't
celebrate together and sometimes they
celebrate two times
uh you know clergy from Greece, bishops
from Greece will go to Mount Aus and
celebrate the old calendar in the day
celebrate the new calendar
and uh she was just a very saintly
person you know she she a lot of people
could say you know my grandmother
brought me to church and all this kind
of stuff but it was it was really beyond
that it was super human it was uh was
someone who um
just loved God so much you read
sometimes in the lives of the saints
It's it you know only grace could could
u aid these people to be so cetical and
um so without any exception it was
always all day all night prayers
she just continuously making the sign on
the cross always praying and and just a
beautiful example which I cannot really
imitate quite frankly because it was
above
uh and and there were just so many signs
of real grace in this person and and the
first few years of my life we sort of
lived in
area of Toronto which is called Danforth
very close to Greek town.
So we lived very close just a couple
blocks away from my grandmother and so
as a child I would I would spend a lot
of time there at sleepover for extended
periods of time. Then we moved and then
they would spend extended periods, my
grandparents would uh spend extended
periods of time with us. And the system
that we had was that my grandfather
would stay in the um spare room and my
grandmother would stay in my room and
she she'd just be praying all night all
all night. And she just like literally
all night tears growing going through
her eyes. I remember you know waking up
with her hands up and she just streaming
tears
and uh it didn't bother me. I was
because you know from the time I was as
long as I can remember um
you know I was very much into uh I went
to church and I I I I loved going to
church and I
>> I said my my mother God bless her you
know she brought us up in the faith but
my grandmother was the one my mother was
pious my grandmother's
holy
and um
so she left an influence in the family
everybody
went to uh synctic taris. She sort of
led the way
and um
as I said it was it was really all night
long prayers and and unbelievable
fasting and uh so I I grew up hearing
things from the old country. You know
how they uh it was almost like we were
in this protected little
>> nucleus and uh she would tell me about
things back in the old country and
sometimes about specifically about the
church calendar issues and how the
faithful and how the grandmother who
lived with her
who subsequently was uh her ending was
so blessed that she told everybody okay
I'm going to be dying she
>> she yeah what happened was that her
guard heard an angel appeared to her and
told her, "I'm taking your soul." And
then she said, "No, don't take it yet
because I need to see Paul, my
grandfather, who was uh it was just
before Pasca, so he was in the other
villages selling meat because we were
sort of well off and he had a lot of
livestock and and um as soon as he came
home,
um she took off her head covering. She
was she was 105 years old at this time.
It's 1950s.
>> And she threw all of her hairs on my
grandparents head. And she said, "As
many hairs as I have, so many blessings
may you have. Please forgive me. I'm
leaving. My guardian angel came to take
my soul. We made a an agreement."
And then um
so and then she reposed right there and
she she told them she made a point
uh to follow the church calendar. Uh she
would not even though the local church
there was celebrating with the new
calendar.
>> Mhm.
uh
then um so that was a blessing for me.
It's also uh it centers me because like
I said it's above what I could ever be.
Then uh in 1988 we made our first trip
to Greece
and as a family and we visited my my
mother's aunt who lived in Kerata.
She lived right by the convent there and
there there was a a famous uh holy fool
for Christ's sake.
Uh and I I saw her on numerous occasions
during that that trip and that was a
real uh deep experience and it was a
real blessing for me
and I always wanted to become a
monastic. So my plan was to go to Mount
Aos and providentially
I found someone
who was uh in the desert uh of Mount Aos
and I had a correspondence with him from
time I was 14 years old and finally when
I was 19 I went and visited him and
stayed with him and I my plan was to
stay with him and to become a monk
there.
Um
the bishop in Toronto talked me out of
it. The clergy sort of talked me out of
it
and um part of me is has uh is bothered
by that.
But I know that uh you know God's God's
plans, God's work, of course, God's
will.
And um this elder was way beyond what I
could ever imagine. I mean I thought I
remember because I had a habit of
writing letters to different shrines as
a child and I would ask for prayers and
ask them to light candles and ask them
to send holy oil and everything. But
when I got my first correspondence from
Elder Joel command I understood this is
different. This is somebody who's has to
be has to have a lot of grace. So when I
went there um I was deemed worthy to
stay with him for a while and they sort
of had me like a novice and uh you know
I was I didn't have a bless to talk to
visitors if they came by.
Ironically, you know the famous father
friend of
>> Kathon
>> from what I understand he actually told
the new calendars that that was a holy
man of the joy.
>> So new calendars would pass by uh while
I was there and um it was one of St.
Narus's hideouts and St. Narus
uh used to go there because the
spiritual grandfather of the Jokim whose
name was
friends with St. Narus,
the elder of Elder Yakim was present at
the appearance of the cross in 1925. His
name was Elder Nectario
and he was uh you know Elder Join
basically was like one of the fathers.
He was uh deep in the prayer. He would
never leave the mountain. He was uh he
would hardly go anywhere else. He was
just there in the desert saying his
prayers. And uh I'm telling you it was
just unbeliev I don't there aren't
people like that. I don't know if there
any if there's anybody like that
anymore. He was a succession of the
older Aayoras the fathers from Manathos
and
it's a man of God really.
>> Mhm.
>> And and we have here his vestments and
some of his relics and and actually he's
worked miracles.
So he works miracles and he you know we
feel his presence. So when somebody says
for example you know
uh how can we not accept u whatever
other elders or saints you know um I
mean this is what I know
>> this these are the people that uh led me
to Christ
and I have no doubt in my mind that
these were just people who were u
inspired by the Holy Spirit who deeply
had God in them whose very presence was
something very special
and I remember just the holy fool for
grac Daro when I first saw it was sort
of like a shock because the presence was
just so strong
and then Elder Join when he served he
was he was in another world he was
totally totally
enveloped in God's grace
so uh that you know in short those
people left a deep impression on me I uh
As I said, I wanted to become a monk
there with the holy other jok. And um
I wasn't even worthy to do that. But uh
I ended up uh what the bishop wanted me
to do was the bishop in Toronto who
reposed a few months ago, God, God have
mercy on his soul. God forgive him and
uh grant him whatever rest
is available from the Lord's by the
Lord's mercy and grace. um
he he wanted to start a small little
monastic community and so he told me go
to Boston for 6 months to 2 years and
then uh you'll come back because I
really never was interested in becoming
a monk in Boston actually.
>> Mhm.
>> And um but what happened was uh when I
brought it up to the uh the yand of the
monastery actually was the ab monaster's
father Isaac
um he really took it personally. He was
he didn't want to you know I was young
blood and everything I guess he just
didn't want to lose me.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh the plan Metropol mar's plan the
bishop of Toronto just fizzled out
and I was there and I stayed there for
around 18 years.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh they made me a bishop you know
after 10 years. I was 31
uh 11 years and um and from the very
beginning I was talking about uniting
with our church because it's one of the
things that all the join serve I you
know I I um I really think it's his
prayers too and his blessings and St.
John who was a friend of bishop Petros
of Atoria
uh because it was right after I visited
St. John in San Francisco for the first
time that things started really moving
but from the very beginning uh everybody
knows this I wasn't hiding it I I kept
saying we need to unite with the uh sen
>> finally we came to the uh conclusion
actually decision hna decided in 2010
that the canonical senate in Greece is
um the senate under archbishop of
kalinos
it was right after the repose of
Archbishop Bros. We sent uh letters of
condolences. I went personally the sit
>> and uh I think that the Lord wanted us
to um confess our faith because it's not
as if what I considered
um a perfect opportunity for them silver
platter for the entire for all of them
to go over there and just humble
themselves like like the former
Cyprianites did you know I have to say
Metropolan Kipos Jr.
Mhm.
>> Uh
uh Bishop Clement, Bishop Ambrose, they
all asked for prayer, forgiveness
took off their panas
and this was edifying.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh so um so that's you know that's the
whole the whole u idea is being humbled
and and so and being humble and going
back because repentance heals. So this
is the reason why I um I I went on my
own because they um
they started fighting back. They didn't
want after afterwards they didn't want
to um
join Arsenad and they started defaming
Arsen. And this is why I recognize this
from the side groups.
>> Mhm.
>> Because they have to have some type of
uh
point for their existence because a lot
of them don't have a reason to exist.
Yeah.
>> And uh and so they're saying that
whatever they can throw out, it's it
reminds me very much of the phariseaical
thing about, you know, just catch him at
his words, try to find something against
him. And so they did that and they're
saying things like we're cypriites.
People who,
by the way, were in communion with the
cypriionites when they were crianites.
>> And now that they're not crianites,
they're pointing fingers. So in any
case, um
I went off a little bit on that, but the
thing is I do want to uh stress that it
was a beautiful addition to our senate
and that they were uh in an edifying way
very they came in a with humility
>> and that's how I went to the senad when
I had to leave on my own because of the
circumstances and I went to the
archbishop and I said I'm coming in
repentance
and uh as I said that's what what brings
his healing uh because uh you know there
was a little bit of a gray area with
Archishbentios and because he was
formerly the archbishop. So on Manos
what happened was in the 80s and 90s up
until his repose there was still a
little bit of consolation going on
between the two factions clergy from the
two groups would conceal at the
monastery of his men.
Uh
but even you know I learned from Elder
Joakim that uh who who personally
respected our church bakant just like a
lot of people in our church you know
you'll find his photograph everywhere
>> and uh for the record he u
he wanted to resign and he wanted
everybody to go under our church but he
was talked out of it by some clergy in
Boston at the time unfortunately
uh that could have been healed and but
anyway may God remember his good
intentions and he was humble about the
fact that he made a lot of mistakes.
>> Mhm. And uh some of the people who try
to defend him like um the so-called
Macarian you know the they used to be
called the Libyans
>> they used to they now sort of try to
present themselves as the Oxentian
faction but
truth you know the truth of the matter
is actually Hopner was they were the
ones that uh buried Arches Bakantius and
the Marian Center was not in community
with Archish Bantius
and so what happens then is that Um
the um
they would bring up a a quote from a
cannon the ancient apostolic cannons
that the uh sinnard can do nothing
without the archbishop but they forgot
the second part of the canon which says
the archbishop can do nothing without
the sin and that was part of the problem
that was it led to such chaos which
people in Boston were saying too
>> up until the point where they joined
But like I said, you know, he's in
Argipics.
He's um almost everybody from his
jurisdiction ended up joining our
church, including his last real bishop,
which was Metropolitan Athanasius of
Lisa.
>> Mhm.
>> And so I went there. I went to the
Senate in Greece and uh was accepted and
and thank God and we didn't have to deal
with the major headaches of some of
these splinter groups.
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
So, in short, that's, you know,
I want to go on and on about all this,
but that's basically where where I am
now, how I got here.
>> So, after you got received into the GOC,
you ended up um this was after Hawkna
basically fell apart in was it 201
14?
in two well things started getting
really bad in uh
well you know the very beginnings of
course are questionable but um things
started getting bad a few years before
that
>> um they always had this tendency of it's
a temptation from the right of let's
let's have a new fight
>> so you know it's the toll house fight
it's the trinity icon fight it's the um
we can't stand father no rose fight it's
uh
>> it just there's no peace this is not not
the gospel.
>> So um and then it finally it turned into
uh and there was this um
awake sleeper fight. This is after soul
sleeping. It's a major thing about soul
sleeping and then they had this awake
sleeper
anyway and then uh there's no end to it
and and we would make decisions that
everything would be overturned. It was
it was
>> then uh lastly it was the name
worshipping thing
>> and my main point about that was don't
even don't even go there. I remember
somebody came to me who ended up
becoming the major uh uh defender
of the these teachings when he was a
novice and I said I don't know much he
asked me do you do you sympathize with
the name worshippers and I said back
then nobody even knew what they were
really and I said well I don't know much
about it but let me tell you that I know
that if you bring it up to so and so a
certain church leader of hawkna it's
going to be the new fight please don't
bring it up to him
>> he brought it up to him and it became
the new fight And so then that became
the big thing and I was just saying why
are we getting into these like there's
no reason to even talk about this. It's
an indication of some type of a
sickness.
>> And um you know the church has spoken
about it.
We don't need to. And that was the other
issue which was always saying it's like
why are you always questioning the
saints? Like why are you coming up with
this super duper orthodoxy thing which
is just going to fall apart anyway? He
said he prophesied it's going to fall
apart.
>> So um
yeah and I didn't I just didn't want to
have anything to do with it.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, you know, you have an apart, which
is what they call themselves. The park
sinn goes to the mother church, which we
recognized in 2010
>> uh uh to solve the problems. And I went
directly to the mother church to the
church that we're under that I'm part of
uh uh a member of the sin out of. And um
you know, it's night and day. May God
protect the church. May God protect us
in the church. And uh we need to pray
for that. And as I told you previously
that
uh it's a dangerous thing to fight
against the church and uh everybody
who's in the outskirts should be coming
here quite frankly.
>> Yeah.
>> As I said I don't believe in I don't
believe in gok.
>> Yeah.
>> This is the go
>> the one
>> it's the go
and those who are groups know that.
>> Yeah. So when you went to Greece and
they were received you were you
automatically made a member of the
cinnid?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. And but were you you weren't
Metropolitan right away though, right?
Or were
>> No. What happened was I had already had
contacts with the Senate and and to give
you a brief history as I said from the
very beginning I wanted to find a way to
come into contact with the Senate and
all I could do was pray about it because
I was told by the leadership over there
and this is my first year so I can't
just do whatever I want, right?
>> Yeah. I was told by the leadership over
there, we can't go to them. They have to
come to us because we're the Gonical
Church of Greece. That was their whole
mentality.
>> Mhm.
>> And lo and behold, they did come to us.
I got phone calls uh and I believe it
was an answer to prayer because I was
praying about it. I got phone calls from
Greece and from America. One of them was
from uh an old friend of mine who I met
on Mount Aos in 1994 who's now bishop uh
Metropolitan Christian. I met him when
he was a priest monk. He was a young
priest monk. He was at Beno when I
visited Eseno under Yandio.
And um
Bishop Maximos of Pelonia was in Harik
and he called me
just out of the blue left a message
there. Then uh I think Father Sos called
me. There was Anastasio
Hudson whom you know he goes to the
parish over there in Maryland. Yeah. Uh
he came and visited me actually because
they had heard that there's a bishop in
Hoffnet who actually talks about the
unity of the church. And so they thought
that I might you know be able to uh do
something about trying to uh bring about
unity in America. And um and so that
opened the door for me because I
couldn't contact them but they had
contacted me and that was from the very
beginning the first first uh year second
year. And so then that started a whole
thing. So everybody in Greece knew me
already for years. And uh I had gone to
Greece a few times. I had visited. I
went as I said I went to the services. I
was there for the 40-day memorial
service of Archbishop Chrisosimos. I
happened to be in Greece.
They were very respectful. The
archbishop was Yeah. I made a full bow
to him and uh they were uh they they
permitted me to be in the sanctuary.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh because you know they also sort
of saw where this was leading. They they
had you know we it's not like we were
throwing tomatoes at each other
>> anymore like they were in previous
generations.
>> And uh so that was uh Yeah. So then, so
when I went to Greece, then it was like
I wasn't I wasn't a stranger to them.
They knew who I was. So I was accepted
and I was made a bishop. Uh I was a
bishop of Toronto.
Sorry, bishop of uh Boston.
Born in Toronto, bishop of Toron. I
don't want to be bishop of Toronto
anyway. Metropolitan Moses is there.
>> Yeah.
>> So that So then what did what year did
you made the Metropolitan? how that go
about your main metropolitan of the
metropolis in America.
>> So yes, so 2010 we had that decision of
uh in HNA to recognize Archishop
Kalinos. 2012 I joined the Senate and I
was made bishop of uh Boston and then um
uh Metropolitan Paul of Atoria who was
still acting met as Metropolitan who was
in a wheelchair and you know he is in a
wheelchair and it's just he can't really
fulfill his function uh as he could not
fulfill his conunction his uh function
as a bishop of the
Atoria Metropolitan and so what happened
was he resigned and then they voted me
in. Um there was a vote in Greece and I
became the Metropolitan of America.
Seems like since then your your whole
your whole uh goal is is unity of the
church now because it's now
you know it's funny because the people
are always you know we got the world
orthodox so it's all there's factions
everywhere but it seems like under your
>> your episcopacy you really united the
old calendars in America pretty
significantly.
>> Yeah. Well, as I said, I I started off
very early with that theme of uh saying
that the unity of the church is a dogma.
And um and that, you know, cuz what I
kept hearing was we're fine as we are.
There's this Protestant ecclesiology
where it's like we can be little groups
here and there. I don't really believe
that. I don't think it's it's right.
>> I understand that there could be some
economia, but that's not the norm.
>> Yeah.
Um
and so the whole idea was that uh yeah I
became when I came it was it wasn't
really much it was just a few you know
very Greek parishes
>> with the exception of father Thomas
Moretta in the wiggo um I think that was
sort of like more you know the American
style convert parish
>> and then we brought in 80 to 90% of
people from hagna
>> and um I was I was just a suffic bishop
at the time. But thank God um
you know most people recognized the
whole the whole purpose of what I was
trying to say
uh in terms of trying to be united to
the church and not fight the unity of
the church. And by the way, that's what
Elder Joikim wrote to me, you know, and
he's Elder Joikim was a real monastic,
you know, you don't
a monastic doesn't speak against another
elder, but there was this agreement,
this agreement, not disagreement, where
father uh Isaac, the abbot of the
monastery in Boston, actually permitted
me to write, tell the joke while I was
in Boston. So I kept writing and I would
write my confessions and things like
that.
>> Mhm. and he wrote and he said, you know,
it was like he was my other elder and he
said, um um tell Father Palmo over there
that uh he's supposed to be working for
the unity of the church. He's not
supposed to disunite the church,
>> which is, you know, it's a big no no for
one elder to speak against another elder
type thing, right? But this is matters
of faith
>> and this is when we're talking about the
unity of the church.
So uh as I said you know I um for me
Elder Join was is a saint
uh and um you know his his voice is is
very strong and carries very serious
weight.
So uh
yeah,
>> so
>> it's a well it's it's seems like
successful because we're now you know
the most centralized and biggest and the
stability in the GOC in America has been
it's not like what other people think
that you know oh there's factions
everywhere and what there's not
>> just take a look at
>> as I said you know search and you shall
find it there's good faith there's bad
faith there's people that are searching
there's people that aren't searching
people that are that put themselves in
position of fighting the church without
even realizing it. And we should fear
God
>> and so we have you have all these you
know we had I became metropolitan and
yes we did have people coming in from
different uh these different split
groups and we have plenty of uh people
which follow the Russian tradition some
the Greek tradition we have you know
convert parishes and uh
and uh that's the main thing is that uh
we we preserve our holy faith and be
united. So if you take a look at the
map,
um these splinter groups, I'm calling
them splinter groups, they hardly have
anybody. And even if you look at some of
their uh websites, they might have, you
know, a number of different churches.
But I know for a fact some of those
little parishes are little parishes with
like two or three people.
>> Two or three people.
>> Mhm.
>> There's no comparison. If anybody knows
anything about, you know, the GOC,
they'll know. They'll take a look at
that map, like I said, and it's like,
you know, there churches spreading out
everywhere. We're growing and we I
accepted a church and now we're starting
a mission in in North Carolina and uh
Louisiana and uh people here and there
are converting.
>> Yeah.
>> So, thank God.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I get I get a decent amount
of messages. I can only imagine what you
get.
>> Yeah. So that's awesome
>> that uh you know when it comes this
fighting against the church that brings
me to the the other issue I want to
bring up about in world orthodoxy is
this whole ecclesiological heresy or
error that's um that's being pushed by
lots of these you know influential
YouTubers these orthob bro youtubers is
the you know I call it the
ecclesiological heresy of the resist
within movement where they're you know
they're saying oh you you go are
schismatic and you're zealous not
according to knowledge and that you must
you must as a as a matter of doctrinal
faith that you must stay in communion
with a a heretic bishop. Can you talk
about that a bit like why where is
>> where have you where have we found such
a thing in the history of the church? I
I don't this new thing of you have to
wait for an ecumenical council when we
see on mass you know some very serious
stuff going on like very serious not one
or two people not one or two bishops but
you know no one really protesting
um when we see this type of thing you
know as I I mentioned to you earlier
there's the particular judgment and
there's the there's the general uh
judgment
Um
those who are already in heresy and who
preach it
are uh condemned. That's what this is
not my words. This is not what I'm
saying. This is what we find in all the
teachings of the fathers. They say run
away. They don't say run to.
>> It's unbelievable. It's really
unbelievable.
>> And you know as I said to you earlier
St. Isaac the Syrian St. Iserian says
don't even read the writings of
heretics. How much more should we not
pray uh with heretics? Because he says
it darkens the mind.
>> Mhm.
>> And so uh St. um Ignatius says it's uh
when heresy enters in, it's like it's
like uh mingling poison with Christ. Uh
putting some type of poison in the
sweetest of wines.
And and he says without recognizing it,
you've taken in this poison. And then
you know what happens? The fathers teach
us concerning u
uh indifference. We become indifferent
when we get deeply into some type of
sin. Well, the same thing happens here.
When you partake when you partaken of
this poison,
you don't really recognize it as poison.
And sometimes you can interpret it as
grace even.
>> And it's uh it's a fearful thing because
it's not like we're saying anything
different. And I want to stress again
that we haven't done any we haven't
moved. you know, we were we were with
>> Roor
>> and um the Rokor, you know, recognized
us and um there's a disagreement that we
had with the Roker, which went and
joined the Moscow patriarch. The the
disagreement is that um you're not
following through with what you said for
decades you were going to do if you were
to reunite with Moscow.
>> Yeah.
>> So,
what's the problem? as one of their
bishops, you know who who belongs to the
Roore MP said, you know what happened?
When did they become unconical like
overnight when we joined Moscow?
>> Mhm.
>> Even though, you know, there are,
believe it or not, there are some
bishops in the Moscow patriarchy that
have been saying things like we need to
unite with the gold counters.
But in any case, what the the big point
like I mentioned you before and I've
mentioned not too long ago in one of my
sermons is that
uh when St. Phil says I believe that the
Moscow patriarch doesn't have grace and
he uh he says I don't force anybody to
to believe what I'm saying.
We have a major issue when you're
talking about not just KGB agents who
became bishops. people who were not
ordained bishop, people who were not
even baptized.
How is that canonical?
>> How how is that not a problem when you
have that bishop who actually wasn't
even baptized ordaining priests?
And so, you know, all we're saying is
let's have some serious repentance on
the part of the Moscow patriarchy and
fix this problem. What a wonderful thing
it would be if we were all in
convenient. But the thing is there's a
reason. It's not like we want to start
our own personal franchise and call it
the church.
>> Yeah.
>> Like some fringe groups do,
unfortunately.
Um we've been here all along, you know,
with the blessings of St. Chrisosamus
and and we have our seals of St. and St.
John the Newsgiver and a plethora of
other fathers and mothers who were who
were uh god-bearing people and who
passed on their blessings to us. There's
there are others that eventually will be
uh officially glorified
and you know there was St. Barthus of
Hios who prophesied
>> uh you should really you should find his
life. It's a really beautiful life. And
Hebrew P is just before 1900 I think.
And
um he actually told he prophesied he
said in 100 years from now I'll be
glorified on earth and uh our sin
glorified him.
>> Nobody else did. And that was written by
father Joim of the patriarchet of
Jerusalem who wrote his life who was a
hyotist from Hios because uh St. Barthen
is from Hios.
>> Mhm. So
he was one of the saints that was added
into the list of saints of our church.
>> Yeah, that's um
when you say that that uh like it's like
when I wrote that book, the history of
resistance, we don't find like as you
said, we don't find that. We don't that
there's nowhere in the scriptures,
nowhere in the fathers, the saints, the
cannons, the councils that says flee to
the heretic. It's always the opposite.
So
>> let's stress Nobody, nobody says, nobody
says stay with the heretics. Nobody.
They all say flee
>> except for the Neoathanites that we all
know, you know, the the five, you know,
that are they say flee to them for some
reason where everybody St. Paul and you
know to Peter, Jude,
>> Thessalonians, Galatians, it says, you
know, total opposite. But
>> well whether or not we should obey man
or obey God, you be the judge as it says
in scriptures.
>> Yeah. So that that the whole that the
other thing that falls within that whole
resist within movement that I've been
fighting against since you know since
you take me took me into the GOC 3 years
ago now it's been so fast is and it's
one of the things that you've touched on
in you know in conversations we've had
together is the the matter of antimins.
>> Yeah. and why that I don't think most
most ley and most people don't know
understand the significance of the
antimins the the license that you give
your priest to celebrate on your behalf.
Can you explain?
>> Well, this is part of the
>> ironically
uh some of those people that resist from
within movement don't understand certain
really basic um teachings concerning
ecclesiology. And one of them as I said
was St. standing nation of the
godbearer. All the fathers talk about
the bishop.
Um your relationship with the bishop is
reflects your relationship with God. As
I said, you know, um what a horrible
thing when people have such a horrible
relationship with your bishop. If you
don't like him, go somewhere else. Why
are you speaking against that bishop?
It's not good for you.
>> Um so St. Ignatius, you know, he doesn't
mince his words and he's very very clear
about that. And he talks about if the
congregation
is under the bishop, nothing can be done
without the bishop. And so that anti
meansion is specifically the sign
literally with the autograph of the
bishop of permission for the priest to
serve the divine liturgy which means the
priest serves on behalf of the bishop.
So you are you believe what your bishop
believes. Basically this is not this is
not you know it's basic stuff. Yeah.
>> Um,
sorry.
>> Oh, yeah. So, yeah, because most people
don't even know what an antimman is. The
>> the mention,
>> the antimention is consecrated. It's a
it's a temple. It's the altar.
>> It's consecrated by the bishop. Um,
we sew in some uh holy relics of martyrs
underneath it because the liturgy always
took place over the relics of the
martyrs. Um, there's a whole service of
consecrating it. We put holy crism on it
and then we uh read prayers and then you
have the signature the bishop signs it
uh which is basically the bishop's uh
okay to serve on this uh antiiments. So
it's it's the bishop's aunt mention it
belongs to him. Mhm.
>> So that's what I'm saying is that's a
basic teaching of church ecclesiology
that you're you're serving in the name
of your bishop.
>> So that priest is supposed to be so
there's that weird
>> he's supposed to be connected to he's
supposed to be connected to the bishop
like the strings are to the lera as St.
Ignatius God bear says. So it's not
normal. It's not normal to have a bad
for a priest and a bishop to have a bad
relationship with each other. That's not
normal.
>> Whereas you have the resis within thing
where there are plenty of uh priests who
simply don't like their bishops. They
might not like you know they don't like
what the bishop teaches and um
as I said earlier you know it's it's um
when we spoke before this uh it's um you
know we don't judge people personally. I
don't know God their hearts. God only
knows their hearts and how things turn
out for them.
>> But um but this is not orthodox. That's
just not the teaching of the Orthodox
church.
>> Yeah. What does it like what does it
mean for a priest when he knowingly like
when you you know at that point in the
liturgy when you unfold the antimins and
you see the the signature of the bishop
and that priest knowingly serves with
like this bishop you know say LP Leaf
Foros this bishop is a heretic 100%
without equivocation
but I'm going to commemorate him anyway.
How does that affect you know the
congregation and the priests like you
were saying prior to us going live?
Well, if you believe that that person,
your bishop is is in fact a heretic, you
have a serious problem. And what's going
on is your conscience is getting weaker
and weaker to the point where it's like
it's okay. But thankfully, there are
people who have consciences. And that's
one of the things that sort of drives
them to uh to come. Sometimes they make
it, sometimes they don't make it. I
remember a case where someone a new
calendar priest came to me and I I I was
sort of just teasing him. I said, "What?
Why are you here? is your bishop won't
let you be Orthodox or something. And he
says, "Yeah."
>> Mhm.
>> Actually, yeah. He won't he won't let me
baptize properly. He won't let me uh
>> He had a whole list.
>> Wow.
>> So, uh that's a problem. You know, it's
that's not a normal relationship.
>> Yeah. I remember that's exactly what
happened when that's, you know, it's
funny you mentioned that because that's
exactly the email. I don't know if you
remember three years ago, that's the
that's the email you sent to me. You
said, "What's the you just want to be
Orthodox?" Well, then
>> I guess it's a common question I ask.
>> Yeah. Like you're not allowed to be
Orthodox over there. I was like,
apparently not.
Yes. It
that was one of the major things because
that's, you know, it's it's start it
seems like it's starting to quiet down
now, but is Yeah, it's the it's the uh
the idea.
>> What do you mean? What's quieting?
>> Go ahead.
>> I'm sorry. What do you mean by quieting
down? for it seems like the argument of
the whole res ever since I came out with
the history of resistance book that the
argument of you know you have to you
must stay in communion with your heretic
bishops regardless of you know him you
know just recently especially since I
put out the uh this 2025 annual
chronology of accuminism where it's 167
pages of every single jurisdiction
and every single action of you know you
know these bishops and their their
prayer praying with heresy, joint
prayers, joint services, ecumenical
services. So, it's kind of I think
people are starting to recognize it a
little more. But why uh
>> unless they've been poisoned?
>> Yeah. So yeah, that's one of the things
is people few people people don't find
that's one of the things that I was want
to ask you about is people believe and
part of this is part of the resist
within movement thing is people think
well I have a good traditional priest
and I've been calling it Orthodox
Presbyterianism. They're like well I
have a good Orthodox priest and he's
traditionalist so therefore it doesn't
matter what the bishop does.
>> Yeah. Well that's again it's not
orthodox. I mean, I'm glad for you that
your priest is traditional, but it's not
enough. You know, he he has to he has to
be connected to bishop. His conscience
needs to become stronger. He needs to
pray about it and who needs to uh
>> you know, seriously think things through
and study
uh the methodology of the fathers. How
did the fathers go ahead uh when they
dealt with heresy? As I said, you're not
going to find anybody saying um stay
with heresy.
So you got to understand why this is at
the very least you'd expect that other
side to be sympathetic towards you know
the fathers do say
>> to do what we're doing but you don't
find that and I think as I said there's
there's a real element of poison I think
that they think that they're do maybe
doing something good but u that's part
of the delusion.
Yeah, in the scriptures it's it's
through all all throughout the the
epistles we see that that's not the
teaching of the fathers. And it seems it
seems like they disregard the the weight
and the authority of the scriptures
themselves. Like you know St. Paul says
if any other even if an angel comes from
heaven depart, you know,
>> right?
>> Why do you think that is that they
they're so dismissive of the scriptures
themselves? I mean that these
>> Well, I'm going back to what the fathers
say. The fathers talk about this poison
>> and I think it there's an issue of the
weakening of the conscience and then
there it goes from that ignoring
weakening to delusion.
>> Mhm.
>> So God's grace can pull people out of
there but out of that delusion but um
you know there's uh there has to be some
serious repentance going on.
>> Yeah. And I I think that the devil the
devil inspires certain people also to
fight the church. Those people who are
trying to preserve I think St. Nico
says something about um it's even worse
you know if you haven't let's say the
person hasn't left a bishop. What makes
matters even worse is that they're
condemning the ones who did for the sake
of the Orthodox faith.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. That's
it's particularly that's interesting
especially for a lot of because I know
we've seen a lot of Roore MP people
coming over to us. So it's
>> that uh the whole anathema against
humanism in the 1983 anathema that seems
to people are recognizing because that
video that is resurfacing of you know
one of the bishops saying well what do
we if we don't remove it we fall under
our own anathema. So
>> right
>> is there's
can people remove an anathema? Can a can
a unification document renew re unh
heresy a heresy? Is that how that works?
>> Well as I said that's what makes us more
continuers of roor
>> in some ways because um we hold on to
the decisions of roor and here in
America you know we basically have two
mother churches. it's roore and also the
church in Greece
>> which both both have a beautiful history
and people don't realize that in Greece
there's a major major history in terms
of saints
>> uh and and holy people who really fought
the good fight and as I've said before
I mean when you get poisoned
even a huge miracle like the appearance
of the cross in the sky in 1925 which
verified for the faithful what they need
to do even that's like nah
Who cares?
>> Why ignore that? I mean, you have it in
the manan a couple times
>> and it's in the manan, the appearance of
the cross, and now we have this
situation of the appearance of why why
did it appear? We all know why it
appeared.
And we had 2,000 witnesses.
And you know, it's I think it's demonic
to just ignore that.
>> Yeah.
>> What would have happened? Wouldn't God
have known that basically all those
people would become true orthodox?
>> You know, and then every 10 years they
would have a reunion and just talk about
it so that they don't wouldn't forget
the uh significance of such a
magnificent event. Um and they uh you
know they just it was like anis the
remembrances of of what they were deemed
worthy to be a part of.
>> Mhm. No one ever said, "Well, no, you
know, maybe it was a star or, you know,
maybe there were some clouds or maybe it
was, you know, they was faced the wrong
way." Nobody.
>> Yeah.
It's that's that event particularly, I
don't know if you've I don't think I
sent it to you, but that um event it was
I think it was in the 19 you know the
magazine Orthodox Life out of
Jordanville,
>> that old magazine. Yeah. They have a
there's a whole issue dedicated there's
a whole section of one of their orthodox
life dedicated to that specific miracle
which
>> right
>> show that they recognize it prior to
2007.
>> Have you ever heard such a miracle for
sysmatics? Did the old believers have
such a miracle? Do you hear anything
like that anywhere?
>> No. No.
>> What are we talking about?
>> Yeah.
Yeah. That's that's just uh something
else they try to pick apart. That's
unfortunate. But
it's um and for those who don't know the
the story, you can go to my blog and
there's I have the whole I have that
whole story there and icon you can look
at it. It's beautiful story.
So the other thing I want to talk about
that other people are actually really
wondering because you know we have a
because your YouTube channel's big and
the GOC is growing is that uh these
other true Orthodox senids we have you
know people from all over the world
other other cinnids and other
jurisdictions that are you know you can
classify as you know within the old
calendar calendars. How do we how does
the GOC how do we how do we approach
that that top that subject? How do we
see them? And
>> I know it depends.
>> Well well we we see ourselves as
the continuers of the of the true
Orthodox Church. That's why I said I
don't accept GOCK. We are the GOC. And
in fact there I I heard not too long ago
but somebody from England who's
well-known writer says you know I have
to admit the goc is what roar used to be
even though he's not in communion with
us.
>> Um
and um I I think it's a disservice to
the church when you have these side
groups. I think that they need to do
everything possible to come to us
like I did. I mean I'm not speaking as
somebody who was uh always in the GOC
like I like I said I was in Roor and
then you know I just followed my parish
even though I continued even after they
they left Rok I still went to the Roore
church because I was um friends with the
the the priest lived close to us and his
son and I were friends you know so I
would go to the church uh sometimes I
served in the sanctuary
um and Um,
it's uh it it does a disservice to the
church. I don't I think that they're
lacking the understanding of unity in
the church. I think they have their own
type of poison. Uh I don't know how
God's going to judge him. I'm not going
to be the judge on this whole thing, but
um
they need to do everything possible to
come into the unity of the church for
the sake of the of the uh the good of
the church. And on top of it, they need
to be very careful because I think some
of them are have put themselves in the
position of fighting the church and
there's no fear of God in that. It's and
it's nitpicking nothing. It's like they
don't they're indicating that they know
nothing about the history of the church.
And um you don't split over even
canonical infractions unless they're
matters of faith.
>> Yeah.
>> You know
um and we're talking about things which
aren't matters of faith. Then sometimes
they try to bring in this whole thing of
well oh these are matters of faith. Well
I don't buy it because it's not matters
of faith. Um, you know, Archerish
Bentius, for example, right?
>> Some of the ones that are trying to
defend Archish Bentios.
Um,
>> in 1984, he wrote a thing praising
Patriarch Diodoros of Jerusalem because
Patriarch Deodoros loved the old
counters.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh and he went to Phile, you
remember that? You know, and um anyway
um they sort of saw him as a different
uh type of a patriarch. And then there
was who came after him. And I remember
all the old school.
>> I was I came across something not too
long ago with Jerusale. And it's like so
sad because all the old school's gone. I
remember I remember them very well. It
was like there was for them was like no
difference for I mean they they believe
we were all uh part of the same church
even though they were in communion with
Constantinople. unfortunately, you know,
whatever it was. But um
>> um so Arishbakio, you know, he um
I think everybody sort of loves him as a
person, but uh he made some very serious
mistakes and
uh so they try to sort of gloss over all
that and then it's like see what you did
see is narcissistic behavioral patterns
quite frankly to use modern terminology.
Um but really deep down it's pheriseical
and I think that there's a real danger
uh because they have not come to
recognize that we're talking about
ecclesiology and matters of faith unity
of the church is a dogma of the church.
It's a dogma.
>> And so you can't just start your own
personal franchise and call it the
church as I've said before.
>> And then from a human perspective, it's
like, well, we have to defend what is
ours. But it's not your own personal
franchise. And it's the body of Christ.
>> The body of Christ is not yours to play
with. It's it's Christ's. And Jesus
Christ, the Lord wishes that we all be
one.
And so I think when I I I hear similar
voices with all these fringe groups and
there's certain behavioral patterns that
are very similar
and there's a darkness. It's it's
there's there's not where's the love of
Christ. I mean you have to have unity in
Christ
and the Christ is the one that wants all
men to be saved.
>> But sometimes it as I said when you work
for the disunityity of the church we
have a problem. And I told you what
Elder Jokin wrote telling me, you know,
you're supposed to be united. You're not
supposed to be
>> So I would I would even take the
occasion to tell everybody return. Just
come back. There's no reason why why
there should be these fringe groups and
think it's okay. It's Protestant.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I was, you know, I'm looking at,
you know, when I when I'm looking I
think about a lot of the s those other
jurisdictions and senators out there,
they don't theologically, you know,
we're pretty much on the same I think
we're all on the same page primarily.
Correct me if I'm wrong.
>> Um,
so what's what's their reason for being
a part,
>> right? And so, you know, I hope God's
mercy comes on all of them. I I would
like to think that in a way we have a
certain commonality but the spirit is
not it's not even the spirit of St.
Ferret. I mean St. Ferrett was very
adamant but you know I remember the
parish priest from my uh parish in
Toronto Father Pod he's still alive God
bless him he's uh it's like 88 or
something and God give him a good
Christian ending and remember all his
good works. Uh what happened with Father
Ponyotis was that um he went to
Jordanville and he took his he was he
was like really close to Archer ship uh
what's his name before um Yakovos he was
he was sort of like an adopted son in a
way you know because he was an orphan
boy he lost his father and so he was
close with uh with Bishop Yakos but he
put everything on the line for the sake
of the truth and he made an announcement
at his new counter parish saying that
I'm going to leave. And unfortunately,
the man that we call our bishop is a
heretic. Just straight out like that.
And the last liturgy that he had there,
I think his last liturgy was St. Tyres
the new calendar. Then he he started the
church of St. Tyres, the old calendar.
And um
so he took a group of people. They
started off with like 11 people, I
think, and he thought, you know, we're
not going to have anybody. We're just
going to be a small little group of
people. They ended up getting 500
families. And Sydney Tyrus himself would
appear to people and say, "Go to my
church." Some of these people didn't
even know who he was at the time. And um
and then what happened was that uh he
took a bus of people to Jordanville and
he was a new counter's priest and
Valikica Verki you know who was very um
strong in his language against
accummitism and who was another you know
holy man um took him in with with a
great deal of love and put him into the
sanctuary and um prayed with him and Fod
says if he hadn't done that it would
have been more difficult for us to join
So you know there's the pastoral
approach there's what's written on the
paper but then there's the pastoral
approach and St. Phillard himself I can
tell you from clergy that we have he
really applied a lot of economia and
pastoral care in many different
circumstances with the intention of
helping people to embrace orthodoxy as
we know it as it should be.
So um that's something else to to take
into consideration. Um, so it's it comes
down to the spirit of the law and the
letter of the law. Uh, God wants all men
to be saved. But, um, so I don't know
how God's going to judge any of these
French group. We don't know how God's
going to judge anybody because the end
it's his it's his call.
But we're commanded to follow the
teachings of the fathers.
>> That's the main thing for us. And uh,
and if we read all the ancient fathers,
we'll find that uh, the unity of the
church is important. and without any
emperor
um you know we don't have an emperor to
help us it's still abundantly clear as
far as I'm concerned it's abundantly
clear just take a look at the map of
America
>> that our senate is really the
continuation
>> yeah
so the going back that that also reminds
me that's what what this with these
other sin is they one of the the
barriers that you know that's constantly
constantly being brought up is oh
cyprianism cyprianism how do we it's
endless it's like it's just an endless
oh cypriion cypriite it's just like with
the with the drum of cyprianism can you
can you shut that argument down for
>> well I think it's another one of those
unenlightened
things of
I don't know feeling better for yourself
with with what you are you know your
whether you're a systematic group or
whether there could be some type
um even if there were some type of
legitimacy, let's say, because I I can't
really speak for most of the Russian
um jurisdictions except for the fact
that we have what we believe to be the
canonical ro.
>> Mhm.
>> Um you know, there's the roach and
there's some
uh but I have a lot of reservations,
especially with what's going on here in
America. Mhm.
>> Um there's only like one bishop in half
a parish or maybe one parish. I don't
know. Two parishes maybe. I don't know.
But any case um
uh
the super they so there's a lot of
information here. I don't want to I
don't want to go on and on, but
it it was a victory of Orthodoxy when
our churches were united.
And um you know, they're not supernites
anymore. And the irony is that some of
these Russian groups who were in
communion with the supernites when the
superites were cypriites are now
pointing fingers at us even though the
supernites humbly came to our church.
like I I remember Metropolitan uh
Cyprien
um Jr. together with Bishop Clement and
Bishop Oxentius in Greece
at the moment of of you know the union
uh they took off their engula and they
asked for prayer of forgiveness and in a
humble way they came into our sin and
actually the first sin meeting together
uh with them was the the acceptance of
my
metropolitan uh title as Metropolitan of
America after we were united. That was
the first the first ecclesiastical act
we did which I mean I consider it a
blessing because
because we're talking about the unity of
the church and I think people don't
understand that basic teaching again
it's it's it's a dogma
>> and so there's no such thing as
cyprinism
um
>> you know I don't there when you have
thousands and thousands of people people
may have certain opinions about certain
things but the teachings that we have
the official teaching of our church is
what is the main thing um is uh you know
what we've been teaching all along.
>> Yeah. I remember when I did the
interview with the Metropolitan Oxentios
and we covered this it was he made it he
made the particular point that even
among the the former cinnid resistance
that wasn't a doctrinal
belief that was being promulgated. It
was according to Metropol Bishop Oentios
it was
>> his
yeah yeah it was his hermenetics and it
was something you know meant for
dialogue and
ideas being thrown around not it wasn't
necessarily
>> um a doctrinal thing that they were
promulgating is and um
>> that's what we heard from them when they
came to us. Yeah. Mhm.
And so I think and it's interesting is
that those people the same people like
that are throwing that cypriism thing
around. It's like they're trying to
throw that on the GOC. It was like well
that the GOC actually itself had
absolutely nothing to do with that
originally. Am I correct?
>> Yeah. So I mean we're talking about just
a handful of people probably anyway. But
um
>> sometimes those handful of people like
to really really shout
>> Yeah. I mean, we're like I said, we're
the overwhelming majority without an
emperor.
>> Yeah.
>> And um
it's, you know, we embrace they're
they're a beautiful addition to our
>> Senate.
>> Beautiful addition to our
um you know, they have a spiritual
backbone. They're um educated. They um
they love the church.
So, for me, this was a victory of
Orthodoxy.
Yeah. Yeah. I think I think that's just
kind of a Yeah. Because that issue
always gets drummed up and it's I think
it's just a it's a dead issue. But
people, you know, the hand
it's the Pharisee trying to justify his
position. There's nothing there.
>> Yeah.
>> How can you and and a lot of these
people consider, you know, Roor
canonical, how can you consider Ro
canonical? They were their soldiers even
more ambiguous in some ways
>> than the superns.
Yeah, they were very uh they didn't want
Yeah, Roore itself didn't want to didn't
want to be definitive,
>> right?
>> So, you mentioned that you know you
mentioned Rowak in America and we just
uh can you tell us about the new parish
and uh they took in
>> Oh, that's a the parish of St. Peter the
Alute. I think it was the only real
parish they had.
>> Yeah. But
>> to the credit of the priest, he
basically believed what I'm saying that
we have we have to understand that the
church needs to be united. And uh his
conscience pangs probably went sky
probably skyrocketed when he heard his
bishop saying we're the only left, you
know, the last remnant or something,
which is what a lot of these French
groups say.
>> And they have nothing to show for it
really. And um
there's this idea of we're comfortable
as we are. It's like I said the personal
franchise type thing and there has to be
some type of um validation.
And so you know it it follows that you
say
that uh the person or the the group that
or the church that threatens you
um you know you feel threatened so you
have to come up with your fair cycle. uh
>> bombs that you want to throw back at
them which are totally just I'm just
gonna say totally stupid.
>> Yeah.
>> You know there's no this is not the
enlightened Louis this is not the
enlightened mind who talks about these
things.
>> How do how do we reach out because I had
the question posed to me this this last
uh on Christmas actually is whose
responsibility is it? is it ours that we
re start you know knocking on their door
and I know that happened and it happens
in cases but for my my train of thought
is like as you said we are the GOC and
they need to come to us and it's not not
necessarily the other way around if and
we can't force them to come if they
don't want
>> well I have no problem reaching out to
anybody that I think has is hopeful but
when I'm pretty clear that it's not
hopeful
Um, and I and I think that it's actually
going to be poisonous for we have
something good going, glory to God. Um,
if I if I see that there's not going to
be any type of repentance, which you
know, I strongly believe because I went
through repentance
>> and then we have a problem. And like for
example, we did have an unofficial
dialogue with the main Matthew group,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> And they're much more balanced than as
far as I'm concerned. I I haven't to be
fair I haven't really looked into all
these other Matthew groups but um
the holy food for Christ sake so talked
me out of
being close to because I was I was so
amazed by the order of the Matthews at
that time 1988 they had the largest
convent largest monaster in Gree 400
nuns
>> and they had magnificent services and
you know archbishop I knew all the
bishops of the Matthews by the time I 12
13 as I said the floor nights you know
and um the Matthewites in some ways even
had more order back then but now it's
exact opposite
>> and um so we had a sort of an unofficial
dialogue and it's the usual Matthew
White stuff you can't even talk
>> they won't accept St. John of course
they won't never accept Stillerette
um you know this is
uh we have to admit that St. Cruso must
have made a mistake. I already know
these things. So, how are we going to
discuss it? There's never there's no
this we're not getting anywhere with
that.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh but the others, you know, um I got a
phone call once a long time ago from um
I get messages from Greece and from
people that from different places to um
I had a phone call from Bishop, one of
the fringe groups in um
in England.
>> Mhm. and um he was very friendly and he
wanted I think he just wanted to uh
establish contact but I was actually
more
blunt than I think I've ever been
because I was because I was I just said
I'm here because I believe that this is
this is the truth. this is the church of
the GOC and u
>> I don't you know years ago when I wasn't
in the GOC I did believe well there's
you know I had more sympathies
especially after having seen like what I
said on Malathos but it was basically
accentiosimos
thing and there were some conselbrations
going on
but um
um you know it just now everything is
just abundantly clear as far as I'm
concerned and the the vision bishop who
called me said it himself. He said,
"Yeah, I think your sin is the real main
sin."
>> Mhm.
>> So,
um I think that when you establish that
point, when you come to understand that
point, that means that um you have the
responsibility to uh to do everything
possible to come. Now, I as I said, I'm
open to talking to people if I see that
there's hope, but I think that there's a
lot of poison going around. There's a
lot of temptation for the right stuff
that's too off and that could be very
poisonous for the good that we have
here.
>> Yeah,
>> I strongly believe in repentance.
>> Yeah, that's if anybody's ever watched
your your homalies on
>> Yes, I talk about
>> all day. That's it's I think that's one
of the attractions that people is have
toward um the GOC in general and the
especially your homalies that you post
on on your channel at Orthodox Tradition
is it's it's not you know we're always
accused of this oh the zealots without
knowledge the zealots on the right when
it's actually no that's not actually the
case for us
>> I mean I talk about temptation on the
right I've talked about it many times in
some of the sermons it is a danger is a
danger Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> I remember when I was personally dealing
with it when I was in Boston and I and I
was in the library and I said, "Okay,
wait. Let's see what the enemy has to
say." And I didn't even know much about
him because I went when I was 19. The
enemy was Father Sarah Rose. And I
opened it up. I opened up his book just
randomly and it was like exactly what my
thoughts were, exactly what I was going
through at the time.
>> And and it was like, "Wow, this is very
clear."
>> Mhm. So, you know, of course, time has
passed uh from then to now, and I think
things are solidifying, but
uh to be fair, you know, there have been
plenty of times in the history of the
church when miraculously everything just
gets back to normal. But I think it's
very clear that we're we're not like
we're not in the best times.
We're getting closer and closer to the
end. And that's just a fact. You know,
time passes, you get closer to the end.
And there's a lot of demons around
there.
>> Yeah, that that's uh brings me to the
question is you know like as we all know
the panh heresy of accuminism is
advancing more rapidly now than at any
point in the recent past. It's it's just
exponentially now we have you know uh
bishops like LP the fora sending his
vicar bishops to go pray with Hindus and
you know the Serbians lighting manoras
and the Serbians celebrating you know in
essence conselbrating with the the
monophosites and it's just it's on and
on and on and on for the what do you say
to the or again the Moscow patriarchy or
you know um just recently the pope and
the pope in Bartholomew doing that whole
na thing. What do you tell to the people
at uh like the lay people in in these
world orthodox jurisdictions, the
communist jurisdictions like who say
like you know when is enough enough?
>> Yeah. I think the major temptation I
think that's being thrown at everybody
is we still have not taken communion at
the common chalice. But again in the
history of the church you never find
such
uh official
union in the way that we find it today.
where you have you have sister churches.
>> Yeah,
>> they're calling each other. They're
calling each other sister churches.
Constantinople and and Rome. Um and as I
said, you know, if you don't like that,
then find someone else, you know.
>> Um a lot of people don't like but but
what kind of a statement is that for the
center of orthodoxy, Constantinople? Um
he received the pope. They received the
pope with the bells as you would
normally receive a bishop.
>> Mhm.
>> Um he was uh received with a sensor with
the candles, the episcopal candles.
And he was commemorated before patriarch
Bartholomew was.
And you know what happened is some of
the conservatives saying, "Oh, well now
just another the usual stuff." What
>> the usual stuff?
This is major. And some other people are
saying things like ah who cares about
the decisions? What
>> since when I mean orthodox you always we
depend on decisions. That's the voice of
the church. That's when bishops get
together and make decisions. That's the
voice of your sinnod your bishops. I
mean it's serious. No no no we'll just
ignore that. Go down to ecumenical
council. Something's wrong. I mean this
is what I'm saying about the poison.
>> Mhm.
>> It's it should be abundantly clear but
it's not abundantly clear. And I think
there's a lot of emotions involved. you
have family and you have this and you
have that. It's not so easy. Clergy, the
one I mentioned the one clergyman that
almost joined us. Uh his concern was
money.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh a smear campaign against him by
the bishop, which happens, you know, but
but this is what happens to people who
try to follow Christ. We're going to be
slandered. People are going to say
things.
>> Yeah. That that that
particularly that St. uh the the pope
and the the pope and the patriarch
Bartholomew. You know, I just I sent you
the book just recently, the history of
the council of Florence and I translated
I had bishop Oentios and and SA the Edna
seminary actually translated the
confession of St. Mark for me and he
says I'm not going to be in communion
with anybody that preaches heresy or
anybody that's in communion with them.
And then on his deathbed confession and
he's emphatically clear, I'm not going
to be in communion with you or anybody
with you. So, and that that begs the
question. That's what I was going to ask
you is people, you know, people first
they go to the well my priest is
traditional and you know my bishop's not
and it's like oh I don't care what the
bishop does but it starts at the top.
It's it's not people think like it's you
know it starts with the priest and goes
the the bishop but it all starts with
the patriarchal senate down.
So when the patriarchal senate is in
heresy what do they do?
So I remember the on my um the day of my
enthronement as Metropolitan of America
in my speech I mentioned that chain that
it starts with Christ as the head of the
church then you have the church then you
have the senate then you have the bishop
then you have the priest and then you
have the uh monastic lay people and if
there's some type of a break there
you have to make sure that you are
connected directly to the church to the
senate which is representing the church
so
in my um sermon on accuminism. I think
it was the Sunday orthodoxy. I mentioned
that uh I'm afraid to think of what
happens behind closed doors. If this
stuff is all public, it's so public.
What happens behind closed doors?
Anyway, um
at the very least, you know, we should
be very careful about fighting the
church as I said. So that is not the
orthodox ecclesiology that you're under
your bishop. You have to have a good
relationship with your bishop. This is
St. Ignatius is not much Paul Demetrius.
You know this St. Ignatius the big guy,
not me, the little guy, the nobody. St.
Ignatius the gobber has a lot to say and
he's not alone. There are so many
fathers of the church. We're not making
this stuff up. This is what we're
finding in all the fathers.
No, no, it's not the right way to do it.
But no, well,
what can I say? You know, everybody's
free to make their own decisions.
Yeah, that's that's what I found when I
wrote the history when I wrote that
book, the history of resistance. It was
when I you know you know how I write my
things, you know, scriptures, cannons,
canonical interpreters, saints, fathers,
lurggical text and and then I started
getting into the patrolia grea which 90%
of that has not ever been translated but
you get into that and it's more flee
flee flee you flee. So it's just
>> so I'm saying at the very least it's
like don't put yourself in a position to
fight those who are actually doing what
the father say
>> but you know being being reviled he
reviled not it says as I said in the
epistles of St. Peter, continue. Glory
to God.
>> Glory to God. So, the the final question
I have is concerning us in the United
States and and the church abroad in the
the GOC, you know, abroad and outside.
How's since you've been the
Metropolitan, how have you seen like the
I know you've covered it a bit, but how
have you seen the church grow uh in in
America and overseas? And uh are are you
witnessing uh in huge influx of I know
you said you're getting calls and and
what's your like vision for the future
in the GOC like new clergy being
ordained and what's our growth looking
like?
Well, as I mentioned earlier, we, you
know, it's it says, I don't remember if
we said it in this conversation, but
before I think I mentioned it, that um
um the Lord wants us to preach to all
the nations,
baptizing them, baptizing them in the
name of the Father and of the Son, and
the Holy Spirit, teaching them to
observe all things.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh tomorrow I'm gone. You know, the
church is the church. This is not my
personal franchise thing. As I said, I'm
making a point of that. That's why we
came here. If I want to do that, I would
have stayed where I was before.
>> But um
the idea is that, you know, if we work
for the good of the church and um and we
want to follow Christ's holy precepts,
then we have to we'll preach the
nations. And we're out there. As you
mentioned, you know, the Orthodox
tradition uh channel is growing and uh
people are listening. And so I'm getting
phone calls. I'm getting a lot of phone
calls and I'm getting messages. It's
true. And um there are plenty of people
who have conscience pangs. But then what
happens is sometimes
in the midst of this whole conscience
pan thing, their voice is the the the
voice of God within them is crying out
to them.
But then somebody comes and tries to
foil the plans of uh of God.
>> And that's of course the enemy. And he
works through c through certain people
at different times.
But um but I would say probably most of
the people who contact us
um end up coming along and u people who
visit you know the people who visit have
life-changing experiences. It's so
interesting how you know they'll be told
don't go there and then you have other
people who come here and it's like their
whole life changes. You know you visit
you visit you visit a monastery but also
monasteries are monasteries and you know
that's what happens. But even in our
parishes, uh maybe not to the same
degree, but in our parishes as well, um
people, a lot of people notice something
and uh they'll they'll comment on it and
and that's God's grace pulling them
towards the church. So I would just tell
people to pray
with sincerity
and that God would lead you to truth and
and the Lord does not abandon those who
love him and those who try to follow him
with their whole heart. This is what we
know. And so uh
uh you know I'm not specifically
judging anybody personally.
As I said that's God's work. He's what
he's going to do in the end. But we do
uh we do need to preserve the purity of
the of the faith so that it doesn't get
so that the sweet wine doesn't get mixed
with uh
poison. So my vision for the church
would be that we concentrate on Christ
and the saints. I stress the saints a
lot because I grew up with that and I
know that that was one of the beautiful
things that was passed down to me from
my grandmother, my mother, my ancestors
is that my grandmother would never start
the day without saying may the saints of
today help us. That was the conver
beginning of the conversation sign of
the cross may saint so and so whoever we
celebrated that day help us. In Greek,
it's a common saying, you know, may the
saints help us. And um
um if we focus on Christ and we focus on
the good of the church and um we're not
interested in any type of personality,
cults or anything like that. Uh like I
said, tomorrow I'm gone, somebody else
will be here. uh we just want to make
sure that the um that we preserve our
union our unity among ourselves because
it's very important because we pray this
in the divine liturgy. The divine
liturgy is the service of the unity of
the church. Union with God, union with
one another
so much so that it's expressed in the
divine liturgy itself. We ask God to
grant unto us with one mouth and one
heart to praise him. That's a petition
that we ask, the priest asks um among
the first, he commemorates his bishop
because who else you going to
commemorate? Because he's the one that's
responsible for guiding you to to Christ
uh by holding on to the uh doctrines of
the Orthodox faith.
And um and then we have this dialogue, I
talk about it a lot, you might have
heard me say it, and we have this
dialogue which is starts with the
epistles of St. Paul grace of our Lord
Jesus Christ, love of God the Father and
the communion of Holy Spirit be with you
all and with thy spirit. You know this
is this is real unity.
Let us lift up our hearts. We lift them
to the Lord. Let us give thanks unto the
Lord and we start giving thanks unto the
Lord in the holy Eucharist of
Eucharistia.
And our life is centered around that.
That's one of the things that I really
really noticed and uh deeply was um
imprinted on me was that the life of
Elder Joen was that in the divine
liturgy. And this was St. um
St. John the Ladder and many of the
fathers say that prayer is the mirror of
your soul. If you're going to be with
God, the moment of prayer is really the
divine liturgy paralons. It's the time
when we're united to Christ and we have
the liturgies going on. Um and that's a
major thing and we have all the holy
relics we have and we have the saints
and uh they they work they're helping us
and we need to continue to pray to them
and have a good understanding of all
those things. So it's like we have to
have the foundation which is the
orthodox faith but then we have to have
the orthopraxia living the orthodox life
and uh and one of my uh concerns is as
the bishop and coming from where I come
from as well where we had this sort of
protected uh where I had a sort of
protected youth and growth was is is a
simple village piety it's so deep so
deep and it's really the orthodox life
lived
and I'm concerned about that because you
know a lot of people convert to the
Orthodox faith who come to us and they
don't have that background
and that's a lot of things that's you
know venerating the icons ving the
relics lighting candles making prophing
candles bringing flowers to church and
donations and things like that
>> I think that the the culture that we
grew up with is you wouldn't even you
can even see the priest without giving
him something a little bit of money that
we you know we don't fall into the
temptation of avarice but
>> um it's a a manifestation of you want to
give something you know love if the
priest comes to bless your house or
something like that or you you know
obviously we do the 40-day liturgies or
liturgies you you give um which helps us
fight a
um and bringing oil to church or
bringing wine to church and uh a whole
list of things and of course I've been
cultivating a prayer rule and all these
things are important and essentially as
I've said and I continue to Okay. And
may God be me with it to say it to the
end. Repentance.
It's the way that we know Christ.
>> Yeah, that's I've definitely I've
noticed that my experience coming into
the GOC. That's my one of the and I'm
glad you pointed that out. You brought
that up is the piety of life is you know
with like Father George and Father John
their cycle of services is it's almost a
be it's almost monastic. They you know
cycle services constantly. It's with,
you know, Father Steven, um, Father
Steven Allen, Father Andrew Kenses, and
and my the Bro priest here that I that
I'm, uh, I confess to here and, Father
Andrew Frick, they're the piety is it's
I've never I I've never met priests like
them who are actually, you know, they
they don't just look the role, they
actually live it. and and it's I don't
want to I don't want to swallow their
heads, but you know, I've never That's
one of the key fact key highlights of
being in the GOC the last three years as
I've noticed is our priests are just
good stock, good quality.
>> Yeah. You're not really swelling their
heads. That's the norm. When you don't
see that, then they've got a problem.
>> Uh and and that's that's the problem is
there's a lot of secularism that has
really really entered into some of these
other jurisdictions. But thank God we
should all pray for our priests. I think
we have good group of people. May God
protect them all.
>> Yeah, that was Thank you for that's that
was all the questions I had and I'm glad
I was able to get to talk to you. And do
you have any final words for our viewers
and if they want to come to the GOC if
they're on the fence, if uh their mind
is still, you know, their conscious is
still pricricked about, you know, if
they should come or not or
>> Well, come and see. Come and see.
Don't shut the doors. Be very careful.
Um and and one of the other themes that
I talk about is downloading information
because if we're going to be fair, you
know, and you come with the wrong
spirit, uh you'll find something. You
always you can always find something
with somebody. But if you have a good
sincere desire for Christ,
come and see. And then we'll go from
come and see to taste and see. Because
when you taste of Christ, you'll see
that uh the grace of God is fully
manifest in his holy church. And that um
if we develop our spiritual senses,
which I talk about all the time as well,
slowly we'll be able to discover a world
uh which is the world at least
scratching the surface, let's say, the
world which awaits us. And that's
ultimately our goal. We're not Orthodox
for any other reason but to be members
of the of the household of Christ in the
heavenly kingdom. So may God grant that
to all of us. And um I pray for all the
well-intentioned people out there um who
are not with us. We're not in communion
with the GOC. As as I said, you know,
God judges them according to his own
judgments. I don't know who they are. I
don't know what they are. I can't get
into their hearts. But um
you we made a good point of St. Serial
of Kazan. You know, there's a difference
between knowing and not knowing.
>> And God's going to judge those who don't
know in one way and God's going to judge
those who do know another way. And then
I think he's going to judge those who
know and who still fight uh those who
are following the precepts of the holy
fathers when the fathers say flee.
>> Yeah.
>> Then that's another level. And I'm, you
know, we don't want we don't want
hellfire on anybody. We want our
salvation, their salvation. We want
everybody's salvation. So, may God bless
and may God protect and may God bless
the work of the church and may God
deliver us from the all the temptations
of the evil demons and their schemes.
They're always scheming.
And I ask everybody since you give me
the opportunity to pray for me too and
for our sacred metropolis.
I count on everybody's prayers and uh
may God keep us united in love the
flock. That's one of the things that I
thank God for that seems to me that um
we have a good relationship with the
flock and that's a blessing for me as
the Metropol that I'm not worthy of it
but I I ask them to continue to pray for
me and remember and understand what
you're saying in the beginning of the
divine in the after the consecration
beginning after the consecration where
we say among the first remember Lord our
archbishop Demetrius. So
and uh I in turn also pray for the flock
and um and my my love to all of you. May
Christ our savior deem us worthy also to
come to the feast of theophony which is
just around the corner. You know it says
in the uh services when we get to St.
Basil's feast somewhere there at the
apothec nativity it says great was the
feast that passed but greater is the
feast that is ahead. And a lot of people
don't know that. Mhm.
>> So everybody should try to make it to
church because the blessing the great
blessing of the holy waters is a major
event and a great blessing. So uh with
that said I thank you
uh so beginning may God protect you and
help you bless us and thank you.
>> May God bless God bless you.
Thank you to see you.
>> God bless.