>> And um but what happened was uh when I
brought it up to the uh the yand of the
monastery actually was the ab monaster's
father Isaac
um he really took it personally. He was
he didn't want to you know I was young
blood and everything I guess he just
didn't want to lose me.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh the plan Metropol mar's plan the
bishop of Toronto just fizzled out
and I was there and I stayed there for
around 18 years.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh they made me a bishop you know
after 10 years. I was 31
uh 11 years and um and from the very
beginning I was talking about uniting
with our church because it's one of the
things that all the join serve I you
know I I um I really think it's his
prayers too and his blessings and St.
John who was a friend of bishop Petros
of Atoria
uh because it was right after I visited
St. John in San Francisco for the first
time that things started really moving
but from the very beginning uh everybody
knows this I wasn't hiding it I I kept
saying we need to unite with the uh sen
>> finally we came to the uh conclusion
actually decision hna decided in 2010
that the canonical senate in Greece is
um the senate under archbishop of
kalinos
it was right after the repose of
Archbishop Bros. We sent uh letters of
condolences. I went personally the sit
>> and uh I think that the Lord wanted us
to um confess our faith because it's not
as if what I considered
um a perfect opportunity for them silver
platter for the entire for all of them
to go over there and just humble
themselves like like the former
Cyprianites did you know I have to say
Metropolan Kipos Jr.
Mhm.
>> Uh
uh Bishop Clement, Bishop Ambrose, they
all asked for prayer, forgiveness
took off their panas
and this was edifying.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh so um so that's you know that's the
whole the whole u idea is being humbled
and and so and being humble and going
back because repentance heals. So this
is the reason why I um I I went on my
own because they um
they started fighting back. They didn't
want after afterwards they didn't want
to um
join Arsenad and they started defaming
Arsen. And this is why I recognize this
from the side groups.
>> Mhm.
>> Because they have to have some type of
uh
point for their existence because a lot
of them don't have a reason to exist.
Yeah.
>> And uh and so they're saying that
whatever they can throw out, it's it
reminds me very much of the phariseaical
thing about, you know, just catch him at
his words, try to find something against
him. And so they did that and they're
saying things like we're cypriites.
People who,
by the way, were in communion with the
cypriionites when they were crianites.
>> And now that they're not crianites,
they're pointing fingers. So in any
case, um
I went off a little bit on that, but the
thing is I do want to uh stress that it
was a beautiful addition to our senate
and that they were uh in an edifying way
very they came in a with humility
>> and that's how I went to the senad when
I had to leave on my own because of the
circumstances and I went to the
archbishop and I said I'm coming in
repentance
and uh as I said that's what what brings
his healing uh because uh you know there
was a little bit of a gray area with
Archishbentios and because he was
formerly the archbishop. So on Manos
what happened was in the 80s and 90s up
until his repose there was still a
little bit of consolation going on
between the two factions clergy from the
two groups would conceal at the
monastery of his men.
Uh
but even you know I learned from Elder
Joakim that uh who who personally
respected our church bakant just like a
lot of people in our church you know
you'll find his photograph everywhere
>> and uh for the record he u
he wanted to resign and he wanted
everybody to go under our church but he
was talked out of it by some clergy in
Boston at the time unfortunately
uh that could have been healed and but
anyway may God remember his good
intentions and he was humble about the
fact that he made a lot of mistakes.
>> Mhm. And uh some of the people who try
to defend him like um the so-called
Macarian you know the they used to be
called the Libyans
>> they used to they now sort of try to
present themselves as the Oxentian
faction but
truth you know the truth of the matter
is actually Hopner was they were the
ones that uh buried Arches Bakantius and
the Marian Center was not in community
with Archish Bantius
and so what happens then is that Um
the um
they would bring up a a quote from a
cannon the ancient apostolic cannons
that the uh sinnard can do nothing
without the archbishop but they forgot
the second part of the canon which says
the archbishop can do nothing without
the sin and that was part of the problem
that was it led to such chaos which
people in Boston were saying too
>> up until the point where they joined
But like I said, you know, he's in
Argipics.
He's um almost everybody from his
jurisdiction ended up joining our
church, including his last real bishop,
which was Metropolitan Athanasius of
Lisa.