grandfather, who was uh it was just
before Pasca, so he was in the other
villages selling meat because we were
sort of well off and he had a lot of
livestock and and um as soon as he came
home,
um she took off her head covering. She
was she was 105 years old at this time.
It's 1950s.
>> And she threw all of her hairs on my
grandparents head. And she said, "As
many hairs as I have, so many blessings
may you have. Please forgive me. I'm
leaving. My guardian angel came to take
my soul. We made a an agreement."
And then um
so and then she reposed right there and
she she told them she made a point
uh to follow the church calendar. Uh she
would not even though the local church
there was celebrating with the new
calendar.
>> Mhm.
uh
then um so that was a blessing for me.
It's also uh it centers me because like
I said it's above what I could ever be.
Then uh in 1988 we made our first trip
to Greece
and as a family and we visited my my
mother's aunt who lived in Kerata.
She lived right by the convent there and
there there was a a famous uh holy fool
for Christ's sake.
Uh and I I saw her on numerous occasions
during that that trip and that was a
real uh deep experience and it was a
real blessing for me
and I always wanted to become a
monastic. So my plan was to go to Mount
Aos and providentially
I found someone
who was uh in the desert uh of Mount Aos
and I had a correspondence with him from
time I was 14 years old and finally when
I was 19 I went and visited him and
stayed with him and I my plan was to
stay with him and to become a monk
there.
Um
the bishop in Toronto talked me out of
it. The clergy sort of talked me out of
it
and um part of me is has uh is bothered
by that.
But I know that uh you know God's God's
plans, God's work, of course, God's
will.
And um this elder was way beyond what I
could ever imagine. I mean I thought I
remember because I had a habit of
writing letters to different shrines as
a child and I would ask for prayers and
ask them to light candles and ask them
to send holy oil and everything. But
when I got my first correspondence from
Elder Joel command I understood this is
different. This is somebody who's has to
be has to have a lot of grace. So when I
went there um I was deemed worthy to
stay with him for a while and they sort
of had me like a novice and uh you know
I was I didn't have a bless to talk to
visitors if they came by.
Ironically, you know the famous father
friend of
>> Kathon
>> from what I understand he actually told
the new calendars that that was a holy
man of the joy.
>> So new calendars would pass by uh while
I was there and um it was one of St.
Narus's hideouts and St. Narus
uh used to go there because the
spiritual grandfather of the Jokim whose
name was
friends with St. Narus,
the elder of Elder Yakim was present at
the appearance of the cross in 1925. His
name was Elder Nectario
and he was uh you know Elder Join
basically was like one of the fathers.
He was uh deep in the prayer. He would
never leave the mountain. He was uh he
would hardly go anywhere else. He was
just there in the desert saying his
prayers. And uh I'm telling you it was
just unbeliev I don't there aren't
people like that. I don't know if there
any if there's anybody like that anymore.
He was a succession of the
older Aayoras the fathers from Manathos
and
it's a man of God really.
>> Mhm.
>> And and we have here his vestments and
some of his relics and and actually he's
worked miracles.
So he works miracles and he you know we
feel his presence. So when somebody says
for example you know
uh how can we not accept u whatever
other elders or saints you know um I
mean this is what I know
>> this these are the people that uh led me
to Christ
and I have no doubt in my mind that
these were just people who were u
inspired by the Holy Spirit who deeply
had God in them whose very presence was
something very special
and I remember just the holy fool for
grac Daro when I first saw it was sort
of like a shock because the presence was
just so strong
and then Elder Join when he served he
was he was in another world he was
totally totally
enveloped in God's grace
so uh that you know in short those
people left a deep impression on me I uh
As I said, I wanted to become a monk
there with the holy other jok. And um
I wasn't even worthy to do that. But uh
I ended up uh what the bishop wanted me
to do was the bishop in Toronto who
reposed a few months ago, God, God have
mercy on his soul. God forgive him and
uh grant him whatever rest
is available from the Lord's by the
Lord's mercy and grace. um
he he wanted to start a small little
monastic community and so he told me go
to Boston for 6 months to 2 years and
then uh you'll come back because I
really never was interested in becoming
a monk in Boston actually.
>> Mhm.